<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The boke of knowledge whether a sycke person beynge in perylle, shall lyue, or dye. &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108908</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844560</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844560</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9384</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16402)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9384)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; I-4:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The boke of knowledge whether a sycke person beynge in perylle, shall lyue, or dye. &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Hippocrates, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Robert Wyer: dwellynge at the sygne of saynte John̄ Euangelyste in saynt Martyns parysshe, in the Duke of Suffolkes rentes besyde Charynge Crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1556?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Hippocrates.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Divination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9384:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 102 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:9384:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 102 -->
            <p>¶ The Boke of Knowledge / Whether a ſycke perſon beynge in perylle / ſhall lyue, or dye. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9384:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 103 -->
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Pocras moſt connyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of all Phyſicions, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the Analogie of al his workes of Pheſycke ſhulde be layde in his Sepulture vnder his heed whiche was ſo done. And where as the Emperoure of Rome commynge By his Tombe ſawe it t<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>helye wrought, ſuppoſed that great treaſure was hydde in it. For the people i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe dayes vſed moch to hyde theyr money in tombes, And when it was opened he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the ſayd Analogy, there vnder his heed, in which all his workes were he toke it away &amp; ſhewed it to no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to Anadeſtꝰ a Phiſicion. And in it they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de medicines moſt holſome for diſeaſes of mannes body. And fyrſte of al was ſpecyfyed the tokens, which foloweth, that doth Pronoſtyke wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her a ſyeke perſon beynge in peryil, ſhall dye or lyue. &amp;c.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>¶ The forſte token of death.</head>
                  <p>¶ yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſwettynge in his face, or pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in hie heed without cowghe / and putteth his lefte hande ofte vpon his breſt, &amp; is beſy in clawyng of his noſethryle, betoken deth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Alſo an experyment to proue lyfe or death.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9384:2"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 103 -->
¶ Put his ſpytell vpon but<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>ynge roſes, &amp; yf it ſtinke h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhal dye, &amp; yf not he ſhal lyue.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Another experyment of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>¶ Cauſe the ſyeke perſon to ſpytte in a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of water, &amp; yf it go to the bottom, he ſhal lyue, and yf it ſwymme aboue he ſhall dye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Alſo the fourth token.</head>
                  <p>¶ If a man ſwete moche in any maner dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, it is good, yf he dyſpayre not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Another and the fyfte</head>
                  <p>¶ If the ſycke tourne hym ofte to the wall, it is an euyll ſygne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Another and the ſyxte.</head>
                  <p>¶ If the pacient haue thyn noſethrylles or the typ of his noſe ſharpe, or a ſharpe loke, &amp; holowe temples, hangynge lippes. &amp; colde eares, &amp; turneth his heed where his fete were it ſygnyfyeth ſoone death.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Another and the ſeuenth.</head>
                  <p>¶ If the paci<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nte put his handes ofte to his heed and drawe his feete vp to hym, beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Alſo other tokens of death, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the connynge phyſyon Ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyen ſet forth as foloweth.</head>
                  <p>¶ He ſaith that theſe are tokens of deth wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the forehed is red, the browes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth downe.
<pb facs="tcp:9384:3"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 104 -->The lefte eye is laſſe &amp; watereth. The typ of of the noſe whyte the chynne falleth, the fete coleth, &amp; the bely decayeth, is ſygnes of deth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Alſo the nynth experyment to knowe fyfe lyfe or death.</head>
                  <p>¶ Take the pacientes vryne, &amp; a woman<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mylke, that noryſſheth a man chylde, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle them togyther, &amp; yf they go in to one, he ſhall lyue, and yf they departe he ſhall dye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>¶ For to knowe whether ye ſhall dye within .xii. monthes or not</head>
                  <p>¶ Lette a droppe of your blode fallin to a dyſſhe of water. And yf he deſcende hole in to the botom, he ſhal fyne that yere, and yf not, but go a brode, not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Alſo another maner.</head>
                  <p>¶ If ye rub alſo well the forhed of the ſyeke with a Tablet, or other ſuche of Copper fro the one ere to the other, and yf he ſlepe after he ſhall lyue, or els not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Alſo of the ſharpe ague an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rymente ofte proued.</head>
                  <p>¶ Take a curteſye of the pacientes blode &amp; vryne, and medle it with the mylke of a wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man that noryſſheth a man chylde, and yf they myxe togyther<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ſhall lyue, or els he ſhall not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9384:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 104 -->
                  <head>¶ Alſo another and the eleuenth.</head>
                  <p>¶ If a frantyke man haue harde ſwellynge without diſgeſtyon, he ſhal dye the .ix. daye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Alſo another and the twelfe.</head>
                  <p>¶ He that vometteth blode, and haue ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge in any lymme, as toghte as a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pette lyke an egipciane beane, ſhall dye the .xl. daye after.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Alſo another and the thyrtene.</head>
                  <p>¶ If the eyes be holowe, and the mouth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen whan he ſlepeth, and yf he be not accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed ſo, and yf his left eye water he ſhall dye the thyrde daye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Another and the fourtene.</head>
                  <p>¶ If the pacient bydde the Phyſyion fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, or ſtretche forth his feete, and caſte his handes vpon his bely, he ſhall dye the thyrde daye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>¶ Another and the .xv.</head>
                  <p>¶ If the paciente bydde the Phyſyon fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well and put his handes to his hed, &amp; drawe vp his feete, he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Alſo the profe of a ſycke man that can not ſlepe.</head>
                  <p>¶ Stampe henbane and mynte, and laye it on his forehed playſterwyſe, and yf he ſlepe not ſoone after he ſhall dye.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9384:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 105 -->
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>of Ipocras begynneth.</head>
               <p>WHo that falleth ſycke the fyrſte daye of the month, it is to be fered of hym the .ii. daye, the whiche yf he eſcape, he ſhall eſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the .xxx. day.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fall ſycke the ſeconde daye, it is to feare of hym the .x. daye, and yf he eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe that he that be longe ſycke, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fall ſycke the thyrde daye, he ſhall be delyuered without doubt.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fall ſycke the fourth daye, he ſhall be ſore in payne tyll the .viii. daye and then he ſhall very well eſcape</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fal ſycke the fyfth day, he ſhal be ſore ſycke, yet he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fall ſycke the ſyxt day, he ſhal ſeme to be hole, yet he ſhall dye ſome day of the next month.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fall ſycke the ſeuenth daye, he ſhall be delyuered without grefe.</p>
               <p>And yf he fall ſycke the eyght daye he ſhall be in metely helth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tyll the eleuenth daye, &amp; then after ſoone ſhall dye.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fall ſycke the nynth daye, he ſhall ſcape with meruaylous great payne.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9384:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 105 -->
¶ And he that falleth ſycke the tenth daye be ſhall dye without doubt.</p>
               <p>¶ And he that falleth ſycke the eleuenthe daye, he ſhall be delyuered the next daye.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fall ſycke the twelfte daye, he ſhall dye the .xv. daye</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fall ſycke the .xiii. daye, he ſhal before vexed tyll the
.xvii. daye, and yf he eſcape, then he ſhall be delyuered.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf he fall ſycke the .viiii. day he may eſcape, yf he lyue tyll the xv. daye.</p>
               <p>¶ And he that taketh ſyckenes the .xv. day except he recouer within. .xviii dayes he ſhal dye, ſhortely after.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf a man fall ſycke the .xvi. daye, he ſhall be ſycke tyll the .xxviii. daye <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſcape.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf a man take ſickenes the .xvii. day he ſhall dye the .x. daye.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take ſyckenes the .xviii. day he ſhalbe delyuered at length,</p>
               <p>¶ And yf a man take ſyckenes the .xix. day he ſhall be delyuered at length.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf a perſon fall ſycke the .xx. daye the pacient ſhall dye the nexte month.</p>
               <p>¶ And he that fall ſycke the .xxi. daye, and he dye not the .x. after he ſhalbe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great peril, yet he ſhalbe deliuered the next month after.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9384:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 106 -->
¶ If a bodye fall ſycke the .xxii. daye all thoughe he be in greuous payne tyll the .x. daye he ſhall not dye tyll the nexte month.</p>
               <p>¶ If a perſon take ſyckenes the .xxiii. day, he ſhall be delyuered thoughe it be with gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous payne the other month.</p>
               <p>¶ If a perſon fall ſycke the .xxiiii, daye, he ſhall dye the nexte month.</p>
               <p>¶ If a perſon fall ſycke the .xxv. day albeit he ſhall haue ſome payne, yet he ſhall well eſcape that daunger.</p>
               <p>¶ If a bodye fall ſycke the .xxvi. daye, yet he ſhall well eſcape.</p>
               <p>¶ If a perſon fall ſycke the .xxvii. thoughe he be at poynt of death, he ſhal be delyuered the nexte month.</p>
               <p>¶ If a perſon fall ſycke the .xxviii. day he is thretyn to dye, yet he maye eſcape.</p>
               <p>¶ If a bodye fall ſycke the .xxix. daye, yet he maye be delyuered the nexte month by lytell and lytell.</p>
               <p>¶ If a perſon fall ſycke the .xxx <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay it is in doubte yf the pacient ſhall dye or lyue. And alſo the .xxxi. daye lykewyſe.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Explicit.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Nowe to knowe whether a wounded man ſhall dye or lyue.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9384:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 106 -->
                  <p>Stampe pympernell, and dyſtempre it with water, and gyue it hym to drynke, and yf it go out at the wounde, then he ſhall dye or els not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>¶ Gyue hym whyte Lettuſe to drynke with water, a yf he perbrake it, he ſhal dye, yf not he ſhall lyue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ A pronoſtycacion ſet forthe, by the ſayde Galien of the daunger of Peſtolencial Im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtume after the partye of the body that it is in, howbeit in God is all.</head>
                  <head type="sub">¶ Another begynneth of the ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes called goddes markes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Whan the Impoſtome is in the pacientes face ſo paynefull that it maye not be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and he leyth his lefte hande ofte vpon his breſte, knowe that he ſhall dye the .xx. daye, and ſpec<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>allye whan he handeleth the noſethrylles in begynnynge of his ſyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes, whan great Impoſtumes are in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of both his knees, it is to knowe he ſhall not dye tyll after the .xiii. daye, and then he maye eſcape, and eſpecyallye yf he ſweat moch at the begynnynge of his knees, whan it chaunſeth that lytell whelkes commeth vpon the vayne whiche is on the nape of the
<pb facs="tcp:9384:6"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 107 -->necke, and vpon as it were a maner of pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der knowe that he ſhall dye the .ii. daye of his ſyckenes, and eſpecyall token is yf he haue greate thurſte at the begynnynge of his ſyckenes, whan whelkes are vpon his tonge lyke dogges flyes, knowe that hee ſhall dye the ſame day and the tokens is the begynnynge of his ſyckenes; he deſyreth thynges whiche are naturallye hote. Whan lytell blacke whelkes are vpon anye of his fyngers, that are ſoore, knowe that he ſhal the nexte daye after dye of that ſyckenes, and an eſpecyall token <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s yf he be payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and heuy in his body. Whan lytell whyte whelkes are in t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e thombe of the pacientes lefte hande, fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e browne beanes of co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loute or pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iche are not ſoore. Then knowe that the paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente ſhall dye the .iiii. day of his ſyckeneſſe. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther token is that at on the mydled toe of the lefte foote.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9384:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 107 -->
            <p>¶ Imprynted by me Robert Wyer: dwellyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge at the ſygne of ſaynte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euangelyſte in ſaynt Martyns Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe, in the Duke of Suffolkes ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes beſyde Charynge Croſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <figure/>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9384:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 108 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                  <p>ROBERT <figure>
                        <figDesc>merchant's mark</figDesc>
                     </figure> WYER.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9384:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 108 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
